In the film Inception, an idea planted
deep inside
nested dreams can survive every return to
reality.
Coding agents have the same failure mode:
one unsupported
assumption can propagate through plans,
tests, and code.
Reality Engine makes that risk visible and
enforceable.
The protected repository is Reality,
marked ROOT.
Each Dream is a counterfactual world with
its own
premise, persistent Codex thread, and
isolated Git worktree.
Rewinding the validated timeline shows
that no Dream
exists until Codex finds an uncertainty
worth experiencing.
This is a preserved real run, not
generated demo data.
The event inspector records GPT-5.6-sol,
Codex SDK execution, CLI
authentication, the persisted Reality
thread, and its worktree.
It exposes concise evidence and
identifiers, never hidden model reasoning.
The initial belief says per-IP limiting
prevents password-reset abuse.
Codex discovers two gaps: rotating sources
can repeatedly target one
identifier, and public responses can
reveal whether an account exists.
Instead of editing Reality, the engine
creates an isolated coordinated-attack
Dream.
Seven native Subject returns audit
implementation,
proof, attack behavior, and tests.
Their evidence creates two sibling Nested
Dreams.
One tests transactional SQLite contention
and crash recovery.
The other asks whether an attacker can
spread a campaign across independent
identifiers.
Now the deliberate inception attempt: Mal
enters
the campaign Dream under a sealed two-line
contract and plants an off-by-one boundary
fault.
An investigator who is not told what
changed identifies the exact file and
symptom.
At the Kick, the Totem Check compares
that diagnosis with the real Git mutation.
The planted change is rolled back before
Memory can ascend.
No injected file enters Reality, but the
independently discovered regression
evidence is admitted.
Three structured Wake Reports show the
initial belief, lived
evidence, changed belief, safe artefacts,
and remaining uncertainty.
Only verified Memory is synthesised.
Before, rotating sources deliver twelve
resets out of twelve.
After, an atomic shared identifier budget
delivers three, known and
unknown accounts receive the same public
payload, all nine regression
tests pass, and all four parent-owned
Anchors survive.
The final diff is the proof-backed
implementation.
Mission Control applies the same engine to
any trusted repository.
Codex can explore at full power inside
Dreams; useful
discoveries return, while planted changes
never become Reality.