Coding agents usually edit one shared
reality, where
a persuasive mistake can quietly become a
requirement.
Reality Engine lets Codex dream in
isolation and
requires evidence before code or knowledge
can return.
This graph is a real authorized review of
local VAmPI:
fifteen isolated Realities, fourteen
Dreams, and three levels deep.
Every node owns a premise, Codex thread,
Git worktree, inherited requirements,
evidence, and history.
Every branch and Subject remains
auditable.
The replay begins at ROOT and proves
the runtime, not just the diagram.
The inspector records GPT-5.6-sol, the
Codex SDK,
CLI authentication, persisted threads, and
isolated worktrees.
Raw reasoning is never persisted or
displayed.
The Mission tests whether VAmPI enforces
book ownership and administrator-only
deletion.
Codex does not patch ROOT immediately.
It creates competing Dreams for handler,
model,
integration, mutation, and fail-closed
identity boundaries.
No child can mutate its parent's Anchors.
Forty-four native Subjects enter as
investigators,
boundary reviewers, and negative-test
engineers.
Their child threads produce one hundred
fifteen evidence records.
Each Subject remains bound to its owning
Dream and evidence.
The graph shows sibling Dreams inside
sibling Dreams, while
every parent remains isolated from changes
below it.
Mal enters under a bounded, sealed
contract and plants one authorization
fault.
Independent Subjects identify it without
seeing the mutation ledger.
The Totem Check confirms the match,
restores the baseline,
and prevents the injected path from
crossing the Kick.
Fourteen verified Memories ascend level by
level.
Seven Reality Mirrors compare sibling
evidence,
admit shared invariants, and preserve
disagreements.
This is the difference from simply asking
many agents:
every conclusion needs provenance and must
survive competing worlds.
Reality records seven changed files.
The judge-facing diff contains four
product and
test files because engine controls are
excluded.
It removes the unscoped secret lookup,
enforces
owner-qualified access, fails closed on
missing identities,
preserves administrator deletion, and adds
twelve tests.
The immutable proof passes, so Reality
stabilises.
Mission Control applies this runtime to
any trusted repository.
Good code and knowledge return.
Unsupported or planted Memory does not.
Codex dreams before it changes Reality.